(意大利语)
你在那干吗 倍波
What are you doing down there Beppo.
(意大利语)
后退
Stand back
我们抓着他了
we have him at last.
(意大利语)
六座拿破仑半身像
The Six Napoleons
手上有什么不寻常的案子吗 雷斯垂德
Anything remarkable on hand, Lestrade?
没有
No.
没什么特别的案子
Nothing in particular.
那跟我们说说
Then tell us about it.
既然你提到了 福尔摩斯先生
Now you've come to mention it, Mr. Holmes.
不否认我确实有心事
There's no denying there is something on my mind.
四天前我接到第一个报案 引起了我注意
It first came to my notice four days ago.
冒斯・贺得逊在康宁顿路
A certain Morse Hudson has a shop
有家商店
for the sale of pictures and statues
出售图画和雕塑
in Kennington Road.
可昨晚发生了一件更严重
But what happened last night was more serious
也很特别的事
and also more singular.
入室行窃
Burglary.
没错
Exactly.
有人闯入了巴尔尼柯大夫的家
A house of a Doctor Barnicot was broken into.
这个半身像是巴尔尼柯大夫
Now this bust was one of a pair
从冒斯・贺得逊店
purchased from Morse Hudson
购买的其中一个
by Doctor Barnicot.
一个放在了家里
He had put it in his house.
另一个放在了离家两里外的诊所里
The other he put two miles away in his surgery.
就在那一晚的稍后
Later that same night.
这还真的挺奇怪
This is certainly very novel.
是啊 所以我想你可能会感兴趣
Yes, I thought it would please you.
虽然我觉得这可能属于
Though in my opinion it comes more into
华生大夫的领域
Doctor Watson's line than ours.
疾病?
Disease?
我觉得是精神病
I should say madness.
而且还是奇怪的疯病
Queer sort of madness too.
你能想象的到么 现在的人们
You wouldn't think there was anybody living,
当今社会的人 谁会如此地
now days would you,have such a hatred
憎恨波拿巴・拿破仑
for Napoleon Bonaparte.
事实上 一些偏执狂
Actually there are no limits
是很有可能的
to the possibilities of monomania.
有一种情况
You see there is the condition
法国心理学家
that the modern French psychologists
称为"偏执的意念"
have called a 'idee fixe, '
如果一个人太沉迷于
if someone became obsessed with say,
比如 他的祖先告诉他的
an injustice committed to an ancestor
有关拿破仑战争时期的不公
during the Napoleonic wars,
他很可能就形成了"偏执的意念"
he might form 'idee fixe',
在这种意念的影响下
and under its influence
他可能会变得狂躁
he might be capable of any fantastic outrage.
亲爱的华生 这种解释行不通
My dear Watson,that won't do.
那你怎么解释
How do you explain it then?
我不想解释
I don't attempt to do so.
看到了吧
There you see.
我只是观察到
I would simply observe
这位绅士的疯狂举动
that there's a certain method
也有一定的规律
in this gentleman's eccentric madness.
例如
I mean for example,
在巴尔尼柯大夫的房子里
in Dr. Barnicot's house,
一点声音可能
where a sound might have
就惊醒全家人
aroused the sleeping family,
半身像是先拿到外面
the bust was taken outside
再被打碎的
before being broken,
然而在诊所里
whereas in his surgery,
危险就小多了
where there was less danger of alarm,
半身像就在原地被打碎了
it was smashed where he stood.
我提到这些
I only mentioned it
是因为你总会察觉到
because you usually have a taste
看似寻常的
for all that is out of the common,
琐碎细节
no matter how trivial.
我不会把任何事看得琐碎无关 雷斯垂德
I dare call nothing trivial, Lestrade.
我一些经典案件
Some of my most classic cases
都是从小细节开始的
have had the least promising commencement.
是啊
Yeah.
阿伯涅特家的恐怖事件
That dreadful business of the Abernetty family.
我可没有把全家人的
I hardly call the dismemberment
碎尸案看作琐碎小事
of an entire family trivial.
华生 你愿意解释下吗
Well Watson, would you be so kind as to explain?
什么
What?
那个案子能够破案就是
Well the point is that
因为福尔摩斯注意到了
it only came to Holmes' notice
热天里芹菜在黄油里
because the depths which the parsley had sunk
会沉得多深而已
into the butter on a hot day.
所以 我不能对三个半身像事件
So you see I cannot afford to smile
一笑置之 雷斯垂德
at your three busts, Lestrade.
不过 要是你让我知道
However, I would be obliged
事件的进展
if you would keep me informed
我会深深感谢你的
as to developments.
听这个 福尔摩斯 立刻到
Listen to this Holmes Come Instantly,
肯辛顿彼特街131号来
1-3-1 Pitt Street, Kensington.
雷斯垂德
Lestrade.
是什么事
What's it about?
什么事都可能
Well it could be anything
不过我想可能是
but I suspect it's a sequel
昨晚他的故事有新进展
to his story of last night,
我的"偏执的意念" 把咖啡喝完
you know my 'idee fixe. 'Finish your coffee
楼下有马车等着
there's a cab at the door.
只给你两分钟
Two minutes.
至少是件谋杀未遂案
It's attempted murder at least.
这下伦敦的报童可要被团团围住了
Nothing less will hold the London message boy.
那个年轻人蜷缩着肩膀
There's a deed of violence
伸长着脖子
in that young fellow's round shoulders
所以一定是发生了打斗
and outstretched neck.
雷斯垂德会告诉我们的
Well, Lestrade will soon tell us.
看看这些 华生
Look at this, Watson.
下面的台阶都冲刷过 其他的还是干的
The bottom steps swilled down and the others dry.
很多脚印
Footsteps enough, anyhow.
是谁的呢
Yes, but whose?
又是拿破仑半身像的案件
It's the Napoleon bust business again, gentlemen.
又被打碎了?
They smashed another?
恐怕事情
I 'm afraid the affair
已经发展到很严重的地步了
has taken a graver turn.
这边来
This way.
哈克先生 请容许我介绍
Mr. Harker, allow me to present,
歇洛克・福尔摩斯先生 华生大夫
Mr. Sherlock Holmes and Doctor Watson.
中央报刊辛迪加的贺拉斯・哈克先生
Mr. Horace Harker, of the Central Press Syndicate.
很高兴你们能来
Good of you to come, gentlemen.
对于我的焦躁 请见谅
Please forgive my agitation.
没必要道歉 哈克先生
No apology necessary,Mr. Harker.
一具尸体躺在门前
A body on one's front doorstep
谁都会不安的
is always unsettling.
你已经告诉他们了?
You've told him then?
一个字都没说
Not a word.
你们快告诉我们到底发生了什么
Now tell us exactly what occurred.
这事很不寻常
It's an extraordinary thing.
我的一生
All my life I 've been
都是在收集别人的新闻
collecting other people's news,
而现在我身上也发生了件真正的新闻
and now I have a real life story of my own
我却一个字都写不出来了
and I can't put two words together.
如果我以记者的身份
If I had been a journalist
来到这里的话
and walked in through that door
我将自己采访自己了
I would have interviewed myself
还要在伦敦报上写两栏报道
and had two columns in every London newspaper.
现在我不得不放弃这么有价值的新闻
And here I am giving away valuable copy
一遍遍地
by telling my story
向不同的人们
over and over again
讲述我的故事
to a string of different people.
不过 我听过你的大名
However, I 've heard of your name,
歇洛克・福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Sherlock Holmes,
要是你能解释这件怪事
so if you could explain this queer business
我的辛苦
I'd be more than paid for my trouble
也没白费
in telling you my story.
我通常要在书房里
A great deal of my journalistic work
写稿到深夜
is done at night in my den,
在那个屋子 离这很近
in that room adjacent to this one.
不知什么时候
At some time
大概是清晨吧
in the small hours of this morning.
那一刻将不断地
I shall live that moment
在我梦中出现
over and over again in my dreams.
知道被害者是谁么
Do we know who the murdered man was?
还不知道 如果你想看尸体
Not yet but you can see the body at the mortuary,
可以去停尸房
if you wish.
哈克先生 你从哪买的半身像
Where did you purchase your bust, Mr. Harker?
从康宁路的贺得逊先生那
From Mr. Hudson of Kennington Road.
那座半身像怎么样了
Do we know what became of it?
门口的警官说
The officer at the door
在堪姆顿街
tells me it's been found
一所空房子的前院里
in the front garden
找到了半身像
of an empty house on Campden House Road.
我正要去看看 你来吗
I was just going round to see it. Will you come?
我们现在就去 雷斯垂德
In a moment, Lestrade.
凶手要不就是腿长
Well the intruder either had very long legs
要不就是动作灵活
or was a most active man.
根据下面的地势 要想爬到壁架
With that area beneath it was no mean feat
可不是容易的事
to climb up to this ledge,
更别提打开窗户了
let alone to open the window.
哈克先生 你能和我们一起
Mr. Harker, will you come with us
去看看半身像的碎片么
to see the remains of your bust?
我必须尽力将这事写下来
I must make something of it,
尽管我知道
although I have no doubt
今天伦敦
that every newspaper in London
发行的各大报纸
will be on the streets
都会详细地报道此事
with a full and detailed account.
这就是我的命啊
Just my luck.
你还记得顿卡斯特的
Do you remember when the stand fell down
看台倒塌事件吗
at the Downcaster Races?
我是看台上唯一的记者
I was the only journalist in that stand,
而我的报纸是唯一一家
and my journal was the only one
没有刊登此事的报纸
that didn't have a published account
因为我受的震动太大了 写不出来
because I was too shaken to write a word.
现在写发生在我家门口的谋杀案
Now I should be too late
可能是晚了些
with a murder on my own doorstep.
好了
Well?
我们有很多事要做
We have a long way to go
不过已经掌握了一件事
but there is one suggestive fact.
这个人没有在屋内
He didn't smash this in the house
或者屋子附近立刻打碎半身像
or immediately outside it.
也许他当时遇到这个年轻人
Well perhaps he was so rattled and bustled
便慌乱起来
by meeting this other fellow
不知道该怎么做了
that he hardly knew what he was doing.
这也很有可能
That's likely enough.
但是为什么他要在
But why did he choose to destroy it
这栋特殊的房子外打碎呢
outside this particular house?
这是座空房子
It's empty,
所以他知道没人来打扰他
so he knew he wouldn't be disturbed.
没错 但是街道那边
Yes, but there's another empty house
还有一栋空房子
further up the street
他一定得先经过那栋
he must have passed.
为什么他不在那打碎呢
Why not destroy it there?
路灯
The lamp.
啊 你终于答对了
By Jove, you're right.
现在怎么办
What are we to make of that?
福尔摩斯?
Holmes?
记住它
Remember it.
写在备案录里
Docket it.
我们稍后在讨论
We may come on something later,
这个发现很有用
which will bear upon it.
与此同时 在我们各自调查之前
Meanwhile, before we go our separate ways
我建议我们先去一个地方
I suggest we make one last concerted visit.
去哪?      停尸房
Where to?        The morgue.
到现在也没能查出他的身份
They made nothing of his identity up to now.
衣服很破
He was poorly dressed
但他并不像个劳工
but doesn't seem to have been a laborer.
谁对这家伙
Whoever's responsible
干出割喉这么残忍的事呢
did a nasty job on the fellow's throat.
杀死他的凶器
Oh that was the murder weapon,
是一把锯齿小刀
had a serrated blade.
但我们还不知道凶器是属于嫌犯的
But whether it belonged to the murderer
还是死者的
or the dead man we don't yet know.
他身上有能证明他身份的东西么
Anything in his pockets to help identify him?
几乎没有
Precious little.
福尔摩斯先生 您在听吗
If it might interest you, Mr. Holmes.
不好意思 雷斯垂德
Forgive me, Lestrade,
我只是在思考一些问题
I was just contemplating
一个我还没解决的谜团
the one mystery that not even I can solve.
死亡原因
Death itself.
请继续吧
Pray continue.
正如你看到的 他身上没什么东西
As you can see he carried very little.
一个苹果 一些绳子
An apple, some string,
伦敦地图
map of London
还有张照片
and a photograph.
照片被撕掉了一半
Well on part one it's torn.
瞧瞧
Look.
长相古怪的恶棍样
Odd looking devil.
跟猿猴似的
Positively simian.
下一步打算怎么办 雷斯垂德
What steps do you propose next, Lestrade?
依我所见 弄清内幕的最好办法是
Well the most practical way of getting at it,
先弄清死者的身份
in my opinion, is to identify the dead man.
一旦我们知道了他的身份
Once we know who he is
以及和他有关的人
and who his associates are,
我们便有个好的开端
we should have a good start in learning
帮我们弄清谁在贺拉斯・哈克先生家的
who killed him on the doorstep
台阶上杀了他
of Mr. Horace Harker.
你看是这样吗 福尔摩斯先生
Don't you think so, Mr. Holmes?
当然
No doubt.
不过这不是我处理此案的方式
It is not the way that I would conduct the case.
那你打算怎么做
And what would you do?
不要受我的影响 雷斯垂德
Oh, don't let me influence you, Lestrade.
我建议你按照你的办案方法
I suggest that you follow your line of inquiry
我按我的
and I mine.
这样我们可以交换
And we can compare notes,
彼此的线索和意见
and each supplement the other.
如果你要回彼特街
But if you are returning to Pitt Street,
请告诉哈克先生
I would be grateful if you would tell Mr. Harker
我可以肯定
that I have quite made up my mind,
一件事
in this matter.
昨晚来他家的
And so there was a
是一个危险的杀人狂
dangerous and homicidal lunatic
并且对拿破仑
with Napoleonic delusions
有着很深的仇视
at his house last night.
这对他的报道有很大帮助
It will help him in his article.
你并不这么认为 对吗 福尔摩斯先生
You don't seriously believe that, Holmes?
不是吗?
Don't I?
也许我不这样认为
Well, perhaps not.
但我肯定这会使贺拉斯・哈克先生
I 'm sure it will please Mr. Horace Harker
和中央情报辛迪加的订户们感兴趣
and the subscribers to the Central Press Agency.
雷斯垂德 我希望
I would be grateful, Lestrade,
如果你方便的话
if you could make it convenient
今晚六点来贝克街
to come around to Baker Street
和我们见面
at six o'clock this evening.
在那之前
And until then
我想借用一下
I would like to keep this photograph
这张在死者口袋中的照片
found in the dead man's pocket.
福尔摩斯先生 这可是个重要线索
Oh, Mr. Holmes that might be a vital clue.
当然了 不然我也不会对它感兴趣了
I trust it is, otherwise it's of no interest to me.
祝你好运 雷斯垂德
Good luck, Lestrade.
我真不明白 我们干吗要纳税
What we pay our taxes for, I don't know.
既然强盗都可以
When any ruffian can walk in
在我们眼皮底下
and break one's goods,
打碎东西
under one's nose.
他同时也让高超的工艺付诸东流
A superb bit of craftsmanship it was too.
偷走笛万制作的皇帝头像的
Taken from a marble copy of the Emperor's head
复制品
by Dupr'e.
请问您认识那位
Are you familiar,by chance,
伟大的艺术家吗?
with that great artists.
当然认识 说到这
Yes indeed. Speaking in familiarly,
您认识照片中的人吗?
do you recognize the man in this photograph?
照片中的人?
Man in the photograph?
我确实认识他 福尔摩斯先生
Yes indeed I do, Mr. Holmes.
他叫倍波
The names Beppo.
倍波?
Beppo?
是的 他是个意大利人
Yes he was a sort of,
干零活的
Italian piecework man,
他在这干过活
who made himself useful here in the shop.
他会雕刻
Oh, he could carve a bit,
做框子 镀金
and frame, and guild.
十天前我雇了他
I took him on about ten days ago
他只在这干了一星期
but he only stayed a week
然后就消失了
and then just disappeared.
他连工资都没拿
Didn't even collect his wages.
也许他跟
Perhaps he was responsible
打碎半身像有关
for the breakages.
打碎半身像?
Responsible for the breakages?
打碎半身像 哈?
Huh, responsible for the breakages?
先生们 这一定是场国际阴谋
My dear sir, this is an international conspiracy.
肯定是无政府主义者策划的
The Nihilist plot.
我把他们叫做红色共和军
Red republications I call them.
没错
Yes.
只有无政府主义者
No one but an Anarchist
才会打破雕像
would go about breaking statues.
他们有打碎你卖出去的其他东西么
Did they break every one that you sold?
我卖的其他东西?
Break every one I sold?
很难说
No hardly that.
只有两个卖给本地的大夫
Just the two bought by a local doctor
和留在我店中的一个
and the one left here in my shop.
至于其他三个怎么样
If anything happened to the other three
我就不知道了
I know nothing of it.
还有三个?
Three?
就是说原先有六个?
So there was six to begin with?
没错 是六个
Six to begin with, yes, yes.
这批来了六个
A batch of six.
我专门从
I ordered them especially
盖尔得尔和斯捷班尼公司定购的
from Gelder & Company of Stepney.
他们的模型做得很棒
They do excellent molding work.
您知道那几位顾客的
Do you happen to know the names and addresses
名字和住址么
of the other customers?
福尔摩斯先生 我的账目
My ledgers, Mr. Holmes,
是很保密的
are confidential.
贺得逊先生
Mr. Hudson,
如果你的理论是正确的
if you're theory's correct,
我们是不是该对这些人的危险阴谋
ought we to warn these people of this...
发出警告呢
this most dangerous plot?
有谁能比歇洛克・福尔摩斯先生
And who better to do that
更适合做这事呢
than Mr. Sherlock Holmes?
歇洛克・福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Sherlock Holmes.
没错
Yes, quite right.
您说得对
Quite right, sir.
国家松懈了
Yes, the country slumbers
但我们仍然该警醒着
but we shall remain vigilant.
是吧?
Huh?
跟我来
Follow me, sir.
在这
Here we are.
齐兹威克区的卓兹雅・布朗先生
Mr. Josiah Brown of Chiswick
和瑞丁区的珊德福特夫人
and Mrs. Sandeford of Reading.
夫人      是的
Mrs.?        Yes.
贺得逊先生?
Mr. Hudson?
什么事
Huh?
您的两个半身像
Did your two busts differ in anyway
和其他四个有不同么
from the other four?
和其他四个?
Differ from the other four?
不 它们是完全一样的
No, no they were all identical.
他们都经过很漂亮的装饰
They're all with a beautiful decoration,
是我特别要求的
which I ordered especially.
除了装饰
Apart from the decoration
这六座半身像
were your six busts
和其他的都一样吗
the same as all the others?
和其他的一样吗?
The same as all the others?
我想应该是吧
Well I suppose so.
你们应该直接去
But you'd have to apply direct
盖尔得尔和斯捷班尼公司问问
to Gelder & Company to find that out.
亲自去
In person.
好建议
Excellent idea.
先生们
Gentlemen?
你们见到经理时
When you meet the manager
能否提醒他
would you be good enough
小心这个阴谋
to warn him of the conspiracy?
红色共和军很有可能利用
With all the busts they have on the premises
那些半身像大干一番
the Red republicans could have field day.
通常我们卖的半身像都不经过加工的
Normally we sell the bust without decoration
但是贺得逊先生要求
but Mr. Hudson ordered
所有的制服都要上色
that the whole uniform be painted.
这是个额外要求
It was extra detail
使雕塑看上去很特殊
and made it a very special statue.
但是 在做模型时
In times of the construction, however,
我们没必要
there is no reason
专门为贺得逊先生制作
why the six napoleons we sold to him
六个不同于其他的雕塑
should be different from hundreds of others.
你看 把两半模型拼在一起
You see the two molds are put together
再用石膏粘上
and filled with plaster
就是一个完整的半身像了
to make the complete bust.
是实心的吗?
Are they solid?
实心?
Solid?
当然了
Yes of coarse
然后它们被放到一个特殊的屋子里风干
Then they are placed in a special room to dry
最后储存起来
and afterwards stored.
批发价是六先令
The wholesale price is six shillings
但可以卖到十二个先令以上
but we would get twelve or more.
我实在想不明白
I can think of no reason
为什么有人要摧毁它们
that someone should wish to destroy them.
甚至为了这些杀人
Or murder for them.
杀人?
Murder?
那么
So,
你们对模型的制作感兴趣
your interest in the molding process
是有原因的了
had ulterior motives.
我想知道您是否认识
Mendelstam, I wonder if you happen to recognize
照片中的人
the man in this photograph.
是的
Yes indeed.
非常了解
Very well.
我们公司一向名声很好
This has always been a respectable establishment
警察只来过这一次
and the only time we ever had the police in here
就是因为这个家伙
was over this fellow.
大概一年前
About a year ago
他在街上捅了一个意大利人
he knifed another Italian in the street
然后躲到这来
and ran in here
警察随后就到了
with the police on his heels.
他是不是叫倍波?
Was his name Beppo,by any chance?
没错 倍波
Beppo, yes!
我从来不知道他姓什么
His second name,I never knew.
我自认倒霉
Served me right
雇了这么个家伙
for employing a man with such a face.
不过他很会干活
But he was a good workman,
是个不错的好手
one of the best.
您还记得
Do you happen to remember
他被捕的确切时间吗
exactly when he was arrested?
我查查工资单就知道了
I could check the pay list.
根据冒斯・贺得逊记录
According to Morse Hudson's records
您在去年6月3号
you sold him six Napoleon's
卖给了他六座半身像
on June the third,of last year.
让我查查
Now let me see.
没错
That is correct
倍波 最后一次领工资是
Now Beppo, last collected his wages
去年的
on May the twentieth,
5月20号
of that same year.
然后他一定是在
Then he must have been arrested
接下来的一周被捕了
sometime the following week.
警察一定有详细的资料
Well no doubt the police have the exact details.
那个年轻的意大利人没死
The young Italian survived so
所以 倍波只在监狱里待了一年
Beppo only went to prison for one year.
他表弟也在这工作
We have a cousin of his work in here,
也许您想问问他
perhaps you would wish to speak with him?
不
No.
我请求您一个字都别对他说
Not a word to the cousin, I beg of you.
这事很重要
The matter is very important
我越深入这件案子
and the further I go with it
越感到它的严重性
the more important it seems.
这样啊 我只是觉得也许他的表弟
And so yeah. I merely thought his cousin
知道倍波被释放的时间
might know when Beppo is to be released.
曼杰利什塔姆
Mendelstam,
如果我的猜测正确的话
if my surmises are correct,
倍波已经被释放
our friend Beppo has been out of jail
至少有十一天了
for at least eleven days.
嘿 华生
Hey, hey, Watson.
哈克已经设下了圈套      什么意思
Harker has baited the traps.        What do you mean?
如果有人知道怎么利用报纸
The press is a very valuable institution
它就是个很有用的东西
if one knows how to use it.
看报啊
Read all about it.
你太狡猾了 福尔摩斯
Very cunning, Holmes.
谢谢啊 华生
Thank you, Watson.
雷斯垂德
Lestrade!
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes.
华生大夫
Doctor.
请坐
Please sit down.
谢谢
Thank you.
呃
Well uh,
有进展吗 福尔摩斯先生
what luck, Mr. Holmes?
我们今天太忙了
We've had a very busy day.
而且小有收获
Not entirely wasted.
我追查到了
I can trace each of the busts
每个半身像的来源
now from the beginning.
半身像
The busts!
你有你的方法
Well of course you have your own methods,
歇洛克・福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Sherlock Holmes.
我不会反对
Not for me to say a word against them
但我想我这一天的收获比你大
but I think I 've done a better days work than you.
我弄清了死者的身份
I 've identified the dead man.
好极了
Splendid!
他是谁
Who is it?
彼埃拙・万努齐
Pietro Venucci,
一个意大利零售商的儿子
son of a respectable Italian tradesman
和一个秘密政党有联系
that involved with a secret political society.
红色无政府组织?
Red Anarchist?
你们一定见过冒斯・贺得逊先生了吧?
Oh you've been talking to Morse Hudson haven't you?
继续说 雷斯垂德
Do go on, Lestrade.
我刚说过 黑手党
I refer, of course,to the Mafia,
你应该听说过
which, as you may know,
通过暗杀来实现他们的信条
enforces its decrees by assassination.
显然 我们的凶手
Obviously our murderer
违反了某方面的纪律
broke the rules in some fashion
彼埃拙在跟踪他
and Pietro is put on his track.
很可能带着那张照片
Possibly with that photograph
是为了确认目标
to aid identification.
他们碰面了
They meet
在打斗中 彼埃拙
but Pietro receives his own death wound
受了致命伤
in the scuffle.
很精彩 雷斯垂德 可我还是不明白
Excellent, Lestrade, but I don't quite follow
你对打破半身像的解释
your explanation of the destruction of the busts.
我说福尔摩斯 半身像
Dear Holmes, the busts!
你怎么老是忘不了半身像呢
You can never get those busts out of your head.
半身像算不了什么
The busts are nothing.
小偷小摸 最多关六个月
Petty larceny, six months at most.
不 不 不
No, no, no.
我们调查的是凶杀
It's murder we're really investigating,
老实说吧
and I tell you
我已经掌握了所有线索
I 'm gathering all the threads into my hand.
那下一步呢
And the next stage?
很好
Awe, well now.
我们有个侦探
We have an inspector who's made a specialty
专门负责意大利区
out of the Italian quarter.
我和他去意大利区
I shall go down there with him,
找照片上的人
find the man in that photograph you're carrying,
然后以谋杀罪逮捕他
arrest him for murder.
你呢 福尔摩斯先生
What you say, Mr. Holmes?
和我们一起去么
Will you come with us?
我不想去
I think not.
我想很可能会在
I fancy Chiswick as the address
齐兹威克区找到他
most likely to find him.
齐兹威克区?
Chiswick?
如果你和你的人愿意
If you and some of your men
今晚和我们一起去齐兹威克区
will come with us to Chiswick tonight,
那我明天就和你一起去意大利区
I will go to the Italian quarter with you tomorrow
耽误一天不会有事的
and there will be no harm in the delay.
你和我们一起吃晚饭
I suggest you dine with us
然后在沙发上休息
and then you're welcome to the sofa.
睡上一小觉对我们有好处
A few hours sleep will do us all good.
大概十一点出门
I don't intend to leave the house before eleven.
我们很可能得到天亮
It is unlikely that we shall
才能回来
be home before morning.
但是福尔摩斯先生
But Mr. Holmes...
与此同时
In the meantime,
我有封信需要通讯员送一下
I have a letter to send by Express Messenger.
贺得逊夫人?
Mrs. Hudson?
齐兹威克区
Chiswick?
(意大利语)
爸爸
Pa Pa!
十一点了
Eleven o'clock.
先生们起来了
Gentlemen on your feet.
该出发了 雷斯垂德
Come along Lestrade.
华生 我想
Watson, I think you've been
你们葡萄酒喝得有点多
overgenerous with the port.
您对您的消息就够吝啬了
You've been frugal enough with your information.
我们坐四轮马车
Awe that will be our four-wheeler.
别忘了带我的手枪 华生
Don't forget the revolver, Watson,
还有小毯子
and bring the rugs.
这次行动不会是
This outing wouldn't be
受"偏执的意念"的启发吧 是吗?
inspired by your'idee fix, ' would it?
"偏执的意念"      对
' Ide fixe. '        Yes.
石膏半身像
The plaster bust.
我有很大把握 雷斯垂德
I have great hopes, Lestrade.
事实上 我有三分之二的把握
In fact, I bet it's exactly two-to-one
要是你今晚跟我们一起去
that if you come with us tonight
天亮之前
you'll have the murderer in custody
你就能抓到凶手
before the sun rises.
我从不打赌 福尔摩斯先生
I 'm not a betting man, Mr. Holmes.
那你也就没什么可输的了
Then you have nothing to lose by it do you?
除了一个好觉而已
Except a good nights sleep.
华生 你要是感冒就是自找的了
Watson, if you've caught a cold it's your fault.
谁让你把毯子落下了
You left the rugs behind.
不好意思 福尔摩斯
Sorry, Holmes.
两点了吗?
Is that two o'clock?
不能抽烟 是吧?
I don't suppose we can smoke, can we?
不能      想想而已
Nope.        Thought as much.
你的人都到位了么
Are your men in position?
是的
Oh yes.
来点薄荷糖 雷斯垂德
Have a humbug, Lestrade.
华生
Watson,
我们可没时间吃糖
this is no time for humbugs.
快看
Look!
那就是你等的人?
Is that who you expected?
他叫倍波
His name's Beppo.
这名字很适合猴子
Good name for a monkey.
他会从后门逃走
He'll leave by the back door.
你怎么知道
How do you know that?
因为其他门都锁上了
Cause all the other doors are locked.
天哪 都碎了
Oh dear, it's smashed.
我想您就是卓兹雅・布朗
Mr. Josiah Brown, I presume?
是我 先生
Yes sir.
不用说 您一定是歇洛克・福尔摩斯先生
And you, no doubt, are Mr. Sherlock Holmes.
我收到了您让邮差送来的信
I had the note you sent by the express messenger
我完全按照您的吩咐做了
and I did exactly as you told me.
按照您的指示
Following your instructions,
我们把门都锁上了
we locked every door
好把他引到后门来
so as to lead him into the back.
很高兴您抓到了这个恶棍
And I 'm very glad to see you have the rascal.
先生们 我希望
Now I hope, gentlemen,
你们能进屋坐坐
you will come and partake
吃些点心
in some refreshment.
谢谢 布朗先生
Thank you, Mr. Brown.
不过时间不早了
The hour is rather late.
晚安
Good night.
Oh good night.
走了 华生 我们还有别的事做
Come, Watson, we have work to do.
别的事?
Work?
什么事?
What work?
雷斯垂德 如果你今晚六点
Lestrade, if you will come around to Baker Street
来贝克街的话
tonight at six o'clock.
我会给你说明
I hope to be able to show you
直到现在你还没有完全了解的
that you still have not grasped
这个案件的意义
the full meaning of this business.
我想你会发现我的黑手党理论
Oh, I think you'll find my theory of the Mafia
是正确的 福尔摩斯先生
will work out all right, Mr. Holmes.
晚安 雷斯垂德
Good night, Lestrade.
走了
Come along now.
到贝克街
Baker Street please.
现在 华生 我要告诉你一个
And now, Watson,I commend to you
适合所有问题的答案
the universal answer to almost all the problems.
是什么 福尔摩斯?
What's that, Holmes?
睡觉
Sleep.
(意大利语)
早上好 华生
Morning Watson.
由于倍波的首次被捕
And since the manager of Gelder & Company
和盖尔得尔公司的经理有很大关系
was mainly responsible for Beppo's initial arrest,
所以我们认为他为了报复
we see the breaking of the busts
才打碎了那些半身像
as a pathetic attempt to revenge himself.
不过很可能
And it was possibly
是无意的暴力行为
the senseless acts of violence,
也许是违反了黑手党的规矩
which transgressed the Mafia's code of behavior
才导致了万努齐的死
and lead to the murder of young Venucci.
这里 我想到了昨晚你提到的
There, I think that takes care
那些细节
of those details you mentioned last night.
是吗 福尔摩斯先生
Don't you, Mr. Holmes?
福尔摩斯
Holmes!
怎么了 华生
Yes Watson.
你怎么看雷斯垂德的推测
Well what do you think of Lestrade's theories?
我相信那一定很有意思
I 'm sure that they are of the greatest interest
但是很抱歉
but I regret to say
我一个字都没听进去
I 've not listened to a word of them.
原谅我的走神 雷斯垂德
Forgive my inattention Lestrade,
我昨晚睡得太晚了
I had a rather late night.
你以为我睡得好吗
Look, what do you think I had?
请进
Come in.
歇洛克・福尔摩斯先生在这吗
Is Mr. Sherlock Holmes here?
啊
Ah,
恐怕我迟到了
I fear I am a little late
不过火车实在是太慢了
but the trains were very awkward.
没关系
No matter, no matter.
您把东西带来么
Have you brought the item?
他们是我朋友和同事
Oh these are my friends and colleagues,
华生大夫和苏格兰场的雷斯垂德探长
Doctor Watson and Inspector Lestrade of Scotland Yard.
您放心地说吧
You may speak freely in front of them.
先生们 您在电报中说
Gentlemen, you said in your telegram
贺得逊先生告诉了您我的地址
that Mr. Hudson had given you my address.
瑞丁区的珊德福特先生
Mr. Sandeford, of Reading.
是我 先生
The same, sir.
您好吗
How do you do?
又是那些半身像
It's those busts again.
说得对 雷斯垂德
Correct, Lestrade.
他有告诉您
Did he also tell you
我妻子花了多少钱买的吗
just how much my wife paid for it?
他并没说
No he did not.
先生 我并不富有
Well sir, I am an honest man
可我是个老实人
and not a very rich one
她只花了十五个先令
and she only gave fifteen shillings for it
在我拿走您电报中
and I think you ought to know that
提到的十英镑前
before I take the ten pounds from you
您有必要知道这点
that you offered in your telegraph.
您的顾虑说明您很诚实
Oh your scruple does you much honor,
珊德福特先生 既然我已经开价了
Mr. Sandeford but I have stated my price
我就要坚持这么做
and I shall stick to it.
谢谢您 福尔摩斯先生 您太慷慨了
Oh thank you, Mr. Holmes, that's very handsome of you.
给您半身像
You're bust sir.
我妻子总是觉得
You know my wife has always maintained
我和这位君主
there is a marked resemblance between
有着显著的相同之处
myself and the Emperor.
我自己没看出来
I can't say I see it myself.
第六座拿破仑
Sixth Napoleon.
今早我用电报
I contacted Mrs. Sandeford
联系了珊德福特夫人
by telegram this morning.
现在
Now,
请您当着见证人的面
if you will sign this paper
在这张纸上签字
in front of witnesses,
这只是表明
it is simply to say
您将与这座半身像有关的一切权利
that you transferred every possible rights
都转让给我
that you would ever have in the bust to me.
乐意之极 福尔摩斯先生
Happy to, Mr. Holmes, happy, happy, happy.
我是个循规蹈矩的人
I am a methodical man and one never knows
一个人无法预测将来会出什么事
what turn of events my take afterwards.
这是您的十英镑 先生
Here is your ten-pound note sir.
晚安 珊德福特先生
Good evening, Mr. Sandeford.
非常感谢 福尔摩斯先生
Thank you very much, Mr. Holmes.
晚安 先生们
It's good evening, gentlemen.
您真是太好了
And it's very, very kind of you
非常感谢 您的价格太让我满意了 我...
Thank you so much, and I'm very pleased of that. Oh my...
先生们
Now gentlemen,
注意啦
if you will give me your undivided attention.
允许我向你们介绍
Gentlemen, allow me to introduce you to one of
世界上最珍贵的东西
the most precious objects in the world.
著名的包格斯黑珍珠
The famous black pearl of Borgias!
太妙了 福尔摩斯
Bravo, Holmes, bravo!
你太神奇了
Oh you're a legend to man.
真是堪比魔术大师马斯基林
Rival that of Maskelyne himself
这岂止是魔术师能比的
This surpasses it.
自从这颗包格斯珍珠
The Borgias pearl's been missing
在科隆那王子在
since it disappeared
达柯尔旅馆的卧室丢失后
from the Prince of Colonna's bedroom
已经消失很久了
in that Dacre Hotel,
大概有一年了吧
over a year ago.
你可能还记得 雷斯垂德
As you may remember, Lestrade,
警察曾经向我请教过这案子
I was consulted upon the case at the time.
我一直在观察比较
Observe and learn.
当万努齐的名字
The moment the name Venucci
第一次出现在此案中时
surfaced to this case
立刻激起了我的兴趣
I immediately became intrigued.
一段时间内 科隆那王妃的女仆
The Princess of Colonna's maid, for some time,
芮什雅・万努齐
had been one,Lucrezia Venucci.
曾是被怀疑的对象
Suspicion fell on her
事实证明她有个兄弟在伦敦
and it was proved that she had a brother in London
但是我们并没有弄清
but we failed to trace
他们之间有无联系
any connection between them.
但倍波和她有联系
Beppo was the connection.
他追求过芮什雅・万努齐
He had been courting Lucrezia Venucci
一段时间
for some time.
你怎么想到这点的
Where did you get that.
彼埃拙・万努齐
Pietro Venucci.
我明白了
Oh, I see.
当万努齐一家
When the Venucci family
计划偷黑珍珠时
planned to steal the black pearl,
他们利用倍波作为
they used Beppo as a go between
芮尔雅和她哥哥的联络人
for Lucrezia and her brother.
倍波收集到足够的信息
Beppo gleaned enough information
于是他独自偷了珍珠
to execute the robber himself
并且携赃逃跑
and make off with the pearl.
彼埃拙・万努齐
Pietro Venucci,the brother,
在盖尔得尔店外抓到了他
caught up with him outside Gelder's workshop,
倍波刺伤了他
Beppo stabbed him,
然后逃到了仓库
he then fled into the warehouse
躲在风干室
and took refuge in the drying room.
他知道他只有几分钟的时间了
He knew he only had moments
他得把珍珠藏起来
in which to conceal the pearl,
否则搜身时
which would otherwise be found on him
就会被发现了
when he was searched.
当时所有风干的雕塑中
Among all the plaster casts drying that day,
有他做的一批六个
he made for the batch of six
是为冒斯・贺得逊特别做的
that had been ear marked for Morse Hudson
在这几个当中
and the base of one of them
有一个还是软的
was still soft.
这是个绝好的藏珠之地
It was an admirable hiding place.
倍波一出狱
As soon as Beppo got out of prison
他设法让冒斯・贺得逊
he managed to find employment
雇佣他
with Mr. Morse Hudson
并且对六座拿破仑半身像
and set about tracking
展开追踪
the six Napoleons down.
他找到并打碎了其中三个
He found and destroyed three of them
但是那晚他到哈克家时
but the night he located Harker's,
彼埃拙・万努齐决定要报复
Pietro Venucci,intent on vengeance,
在和他说话时
accosted him and this time
倍波割断了他的喉咙
Beppo slit his throat.
只剩下两个半身像了
With only two busts left
他很可能会
it was likely he would
先找伦敦这个
try the London one first.
因此我们去了齐兹威克区
Hence our visit to Chiswick.
说得没错 华生
Exactly, Watson.
只剩下在瑞丁区的半身像了
That left only the Reading bust.
所以我当着你们的面把它买来
I bought it in your presence from the owner
就在那
and there it lies.
福尔摩斯先生
Well, Mr. Holmes.
我见过您处理很多案件
I've seen you handle a good many cases in my time
但我不像
but I don't know that I ever knew
这件案子处理得那么巧妙
a more workman like one than this.
我们苏格兰场的人 你要知道
We're not jealous of you, you know,
并不是嫉妒你
at Scotland Yard.
我们以您为骄傲
I will say we're proud of you.
如果您明天早上能来的话
And if you come down tomorrow
我想所有人 无论老的
there's not a man from the oldest inspector
还是年轻的警察
to the youngest constable,
都会很高兴
who wouldn't be glad
和您握手祝贺的
to shake you by the hand.
谢谢
Thank you.
你能把康克-辛格尔顿伪造案的
Would you get down the
文件拿出来吗
Conk-Singleton forgery case,
华生?
please Watson?
再见 雷斯垂德
Goodbye, Lestrade
如果你遇到任何问题
and if any little problem comes your way
我都将
I shall be happy, if I can,
尽可能帮你解决的
to give you a hint or two as to its solution.
处死通告
本席现在宣判对倍波・西柯里尼执行环首之刑
在本人的监督下择日施行
-==http://www.ragbear.com==-